Guide to the Cass Gilbert Collection 1883-1952 (Bulk 1900-1934 ) PR 21
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Project Files, 21738
  - Subseries II: Bound Volumes, 21751
    - Chase Manufacturing Company Offices, 1916-1920; 21811 (Volume 27-29)
    - Chase Memorial Dispensary, 1923-1924; 21810 (Volume 30)
    - Detroit Public Library, 1913-1922; 21809 (Volume 31-36)
    - Essex Country Courthouse, 1901-1907; 21808 (Volume 37-42)
    - Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis, 1921-1925; 21807 (Volume 43-46)
    - First Division Memorial, 1924-1935; 21806 (Volume 47)
    - Floranada Club, 1925-1926; 21805 (Volume 48)
    - G. Fox and Co. Department Store, 1917; 21804 (Volume 49-50)
    - Helena Hotel, 1912; 21803 (Volume 51)
    - Hotchkiss School, 1914-1930; 21802 (Volume 52-57)
    - Hudson River Bridge, 1926-1934; 21801 (Volume 58-60)
    - Interzone Building, 1923-1931; 21800 (Volume 61-64)
    - Ives Memorial Library, 1908-1911; 21799 (Volume 65-68)
    - James House, 1931-1932; 21798 (Volume 69)
    - Kill Van Kull Bridge, 1926-1934; 21797 (Volume 70-71)
    - Kinney Building, 1912-1931; 21796 (Volume 72-81)
    - Louisiana Purchase Exposition, 1901-1916; 21795 (Volume 82-84)
    - Minnesota State Capital, 1902-1907; 21794 (Volume 85-103)
    - Montana Club, 1904-1905; 21793 (Volume 104)
    - National State Savings Bank, 1910-1915; 21792 (Volume 105-107)
    - New York County Lawyer's Association, 1929; 21791 (Volume 108-110)
    - New York Life Insurance Building, 1924-1936; 21790 (Volume 111-125)
    - New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Stations- Bartow Station, 1910-1918; 21789 (Volume 126)
    - New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Stations- New Haven Station, 1917-1919; 21788 (Volume 127-129)
    - Oberlin College, 1905-1930; 21787 (Volume 130-143)
    - 130 West 30th Street, 1927-1929; 21786 (Volume 144)
    - Prudential Life Insurance Company Bridges and Buildings, 1925-1934; 21785 (Volume 145-161)
    - Rodin Studios, 1916-1918; 21784 (Volume 162-165)
    - Sailor's Snug Harbor Apartments, 1922; 21783 (Volume 166)
    - Saint Louis First National Bank, 1919-1921; 21782 (Volume 167)
    - Saint Louis Hotel, 1908-1909; 21781 (Volume 168)
    - Saint Louis Public Library, 1907-1916; 21780 (Volume 169-178)
    - Saint Peter's Hospital, 1909-1910; 21779 (Volume 179)
    - Scheuer Building, 1904-1906; 21778 (Volume 180)
    - School of Industrial Arts, 1909-1910; 21777 (Volume 181-183)
    - Scott Fountain and Belle Isle Bridge, 1914-1932; 21776 (Volume 184-188)
    - Scoville Manufacturing Company, 1917-1920; 21775 (Volume 189)
    - Seaside Sanatorium, 1931-1935; 21774 (Volume 190-206)
    - Spaulding Building, 1909-1916; 21773 (Volume 207-208)
    - Union Central Life Insurance Building, 1911-1913; 21772 (Volume 209-215)
    - Union Club, 1900-1914; 21771 (Volume 216-223)
    - United States Army Supply Base, 1918-1919; 21770 (Volume 224-226)
    - United States Chamber of Commerce, 1919-1925; 21769 (Volume 227-234)
    - United States Court House, 1932; 21768 (Volume 235)
    - United States Custom House, 1899-1921; 21767 (Volume 236-255)
    - United States Legation Building, 1926-1932; 21766 (Volume 256-257)
    - United States Supreme Court Building, 1921-1938; 21765 (Volume 258-269)
    - United States Treasury Department Annex, 1918-1921; 21764 (Volume 270-272)
    - University of Minnesota, 1909-1911; 21763 (Volume 273)
    - University of Texas, 1910-1922; 21762 (Volume 274-277)
    - Waterbury Club, 1917-1918; 21761 (Volume 278)
    - Waterbury Municipal Building, 1914-1921; 21760 (Volume 279-284)
    - Waterbury National Bank, 1919-1922; 21759 (Volume 285-291)
    - West Street Building, 1906-1909; 21758 (Volume 292-294)
    - West Virginia State Capitol, 1921-1931; 21757 (Volume 295-306)
    - Williams Warehouse, 1927-1928; 21756 (Volume 307-308)
    - Wisconsin State Capitol, 1905-1907; 21755 (Volume 309)
    - Woolworth Building, 1910-1913; 21754 (Volume 310-322)
    - Woolworth Memorial Church, 1912-1915; 21753 (Volume 323)
    - Various Projects, 1892-1925; 21752 (Volume 324-341)
  - Subseries III: Oversize Material, 21739
    The oversize material includes loose items as well as bound scrapbooks relating to Cass Gilbert's projects. The material consists of photographs, drawings and books of newspaper clippings.
    - Charleston Public Library- Drawings, 1906; 21750 (Box 681)
    - Kill Van Kull Bridge- Drawings, 1928; 21749 (Box 681)
    - National State Bank- Photographs, Undated; 21748 (Box 681)
    - Minnesota State Capitol- Photographs, 1897-1903; 21747 (Box 681)
    - United States Custom House- Photographs of Interior and Exterior, 1907; 21746 (Box 681)
    - University of Minnesota- Photographs, 1909; 21745 (Box 681)
    - Woolworth Building- Photographs and Drawings, 1911; 21744 (Box 681, Folder 15)
    - Austin Nichols Building (Box 681, Folder 16)
      Scope and Contents
      photograph of the interior of an office at Austin Nichols and Co., donated by the grandaughter of William S. Watson, who worked at Austin Nichols for 47 years. The man in glasses appears to be Cass Gilbert.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Paula Watson Elliott, 2007.
    - Unidentified Bridges and Buildings, Undated; 21743 (Box 681, Folder 17)
    - Woolworth Building, Dinner Given in Honor of Cass Gilbert by Mr. Woolworth - Photograph (2 copies), 1913; 59436 (Box PR52)
      Location note
      There are two copies of this photograph, both held in the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections, in PR52, Portrait File, Group Portraits (Flat files, Large), Commercial Activities. These photographs are not part of the original collection and were donated separately.
    - Minnesota State Capitol- Newspaper Clippings Book, 1903-1905; 21742 (Box 682)
    - West Virginia State Capitol- Clippings Book, 1920-1925; 21741 (Box 683)
    - United States Supreme Court Building- Photographs of Building Models and Cabinet Sketches, 1931; 21740 (Box 684)
- Series II. Office Files, 21668
  This series includes all administrative files relating to Gilbert's professional career and the running of his office. This includes information on his employees, the products and services used by the office, and the different office spaces inhabited by the architecture firm. The office files also document Gilbert's outside professional work such as serving as a judge for architecture competitions, advising on city planning, and his opposition to a plan to build a power plant in Washington D.C. Most of the files are designated #103.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 21703
    The office correspondence is mostly incoming and any significant amounts of outgoing copies are filed separately. The letters are filed by date and then by correspondent. The general office correspondence consists of letters regarding potential projects, businesses promoting their products, and orders for supplies. Correspondence regarding workers consists of letters of introduction, men's letters asking for work, and a set of letters from office employees who want recommendations to serve in World War I. The correspondence also includes professional matters such as asking Cass Gilbert to speak at events or to judge architecture competitions. This subseries includes letters from Cass Gilbert Jr. if they relate to the business. Personal letters from Cass Gilbert, Jr. can be found in Series IV.
    - Office Correspondence, Undated, 1892-1900; 21737 (Box 566)
    - Office Correspondence, 1900-1902; 21736 (Box 567)
    - Office Correspondence, 1902-1903; 21735 (Box 568)
    - Office Correspondence, 1903-1905; 21734 (Box 569)
    - Office Correspondence, 1906-1907; 21733 (Box 570)
    - Office Correspondence, 1907-1908; 21732 (Box 571)
    - Office Correspondence, 1908-1909; 21731 (Box 572)
    - Office Correspondence, 1910-1911; 21730 (Box 573)
    - Office Correspondence, 1911; 21729 (Box 574)
    - Office Correspondence, 1911-1912; 21728 (Box 575)
    - Office Correspondence, 1912-1913; 21727 (Box 576)
    - Office Correspondence, 1913-1914; 21726 (Box 577)
    - Office Correspondence, 1914-1915; 21725 (Box 578)
    - Office Correspondence, 1915; 21724 (Box 579)
    - Office Correspondence, 1916; 21723 (Box 580)
    - Office Correspondence, 1916-1917; 21722 (Box 581)
    - Office Correspondence, 1917-1918; 21721 (Box 582)
    - Office Correspondence, 1918-1919; 21720 (Box 583)
    - Office Correspondence, 1919-1920; 21719 (Box 584)
    - Office Correspondence, 1920-1921; 21718 (Box 585)
    - Office Correspondence, 1921-1922; 21717 (Box 586)
    - Office Correspondence, 1922-1923; 21716 (Box 587)
    - Office Correspondence, 1923-1924; 21715 (Box 588)
    - Office Correspondence, 1924-1925; 21714 (Box 589)
    - Office Correspondence, 1925-1926; 21713 (Box 590)
    - Office Correspondence, 1926-1927; 21712 (Box 591)
    - Office Correspondence, 1927-1928; 21711 (Box 592)
    - Office Correspondence, 1928-1929; 21710 (Box 593)
    - Office Correspondence, 1929-1930; 21709 (Box 594)
    - Office Correspondence, 1930-1931; 21708 (Box 595)
    - Office Correspondence, 1931-1932; 21707 (Box 596)
    - Office Correspondence, 1932-1933; 21706 (Box 597)
    - Office Correspondence, 1933-1934; 21705 (Box 598)
    - Office Correspondence, 1934; 21704 (Box 599)
  - Subseries II: Memoranda, 21701
    This subseries contains memoranda regarding office procedures, office spaces, the documentation of phone calls, and the discussion of possible projects.
    - Memoranda, 1900-1934; 21702 (Box 599-600)
  - Subseries III: Reports, 21699
    The reports in this subseries relate to Gilbert's office, business, or planning strategies for New York City and Washington, DC.
    - Reports, 1923-1932; 21700 (Box 600-601)
  - Subseries IV: Contracts/Agreements, 21696
    This subseries contains contracts and agreements for services and office space.
    - Contracts, Undated, 1904-1916; 21698 (Box 601)
    - Agreements for Office Space, 1901-1935; 21697 (Box 601)
  - Subseries V.: Financial Documents, 21689
    The financial documents relate to employee payments, rents for office space, and payments for general goods and services.
    - Payroll Records, 1912-1928; 21695 (Box 601-604)
    - Distribution and Notes re Salaries, 1912-1931; 21694 (Box 604)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1899-1933; 21693 (Box 604-605)
    - Vouchers, 1922-1923; 21692 (Box 605-606)
    - Petty Cash Accounts, 1900-1908; 21691 (Box 606)
    - Payments for Office Space, 1902-1906; 21690 (Box 606)
  - Subseries VI: Calendars, 21687
    This subseries includes weekly calendars with space for a daily agenda. The calendars document his meetings, travel plans, and what he completed in the office for a particular day.
    - Weekly Appointment Calendars, 1914-1934; 21688 (Box 607-608)
  - Subseries VII: Publications, 21685
    This subseries includes offers from various magazines for the publication of plans or for subscriptions to the magazine.
    - Various Publications, 1900-1907; 21686 (Box 608)
  - Subseries VIII: Clippings, 21683
    The clippings in this subseries include articles related to the architectural projects of Gilbert's office or by other architects. The subseries also contains clippings regarding the proposed power plant in Washington D.C. and city plans for New York City.
    - Clippings, 1901-1931; 21684 (Box 608)
  - Subseries IX: Other Material, 21681
    This subseries contains other office and professional files. It includes documents regarding the NYC Regional Plan, the Washington DC Power Plant Site, office spaces, office policies, employees, John Rockart vs. Cass Gilbert Inc., etc.
    - Miscellaneous Office Files, 1900-1937; 21682 (Box 609-610)
  - Subseries X: Bound Volumes, 21673
    Most of the volumes are letterbooks that contain copies of outgoing letters from Gilbert's office. Other volumes include contract records, cash books, journals of expenses, records of work, payroll ledgers, and a transcript from James Stewart & Co. vs. US Claims Court. Many of these volumes are fragile and access is dependent upon the judgment of the print room staff.
    - Letterbooks, 1883-1937; 21680 (Volume 343-371)
    - Contract Records, 1909-1937; 21679 (Volume 372)
    - Cash Books, 1883-1934; 21678 (Volume 373-380)
    - Journals of Expenses, 1903-1934; 21677 (Volume 381-383)
    - Records of Work, 1891-1908; 21676 (Volume 384-385)
    - Payroll Ledger, 1928-1935; 21675 (Volume 386)
    - Cass Gilbert Jr. Testimony for the Plaintiff in James Stewart & Co. vs. US Claims Court, Volume I, 1942; 21674 (Volume 387)
  - Subseries XI: Oversize Materials, 21669
    The oversize materials include a brochure on the Hollar Company, a copy of Skyscrapers of New York by Vernon Howe Bailey, service sheets by the Architectural Service Corporation, and a photograph of the artists at the Columbian Exposition Building.
    - Brochure on Hollar Company, [1920]; 21672 (Box 685)
    - Skyscrapers of New York by Vernon Howe Bailey with introduction by Cass Gilbert, 1923; 21671 (Box 685)
    - Service Sheets by the Architectural Service Corporation, 1916-1919; 21670 (Box 685)
- Series III. Professional Organizations, 21621
  This series includes documents relating to Cass Gilbert's involvement in art and architectural organizations. Files relating to his participation in other organizations or causes are located within his personal files. The organizations most heavily represented are the American Institute of Architects, the Commission of Fine Arts, and the National Academy of Design.
  - Subseries I. Foldered Material:, 21626
    Most of the subseries consists of correspondence but memoranda, reports and brochures are also included. The files regarding the American Institute of Architects include materials on the national organization as well as the state and local chapters. The files also include correspondence regarding his resignation from the AIA.
    - Alpha Rho Chi, 1924-1934; 21667 (Box 610)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1915-1934; 21666 (Box 610-611)
    - American Academy in Rome, 1905-1925; 21665 (Box 611-612)
    - American Artists' Committee of One Hundred, 1916-1922; 21664 (Box 612)
    - American Federation of Arts, 1910-1934; 21663 (Box 612-613)
    - American Institute of Architects, 1901-1936; 21662 (Box 613-619)
    - Architectural Arts League, 1910; 21661 (Box 620)
    - Architectural Exhibits, 1916-1934; 21660 (Box 620)
    - Architectural League of America, 1908; 21659 (Box 620)
    - Architectural League of New York, 1899-1934; 21658 (Box 620-621)
    - Architectural League of the Pacific Coast, 1909; 21657 (Box 621)
    - Architects Emergency Committee, 1932-1933; 21656 (Box 621)
    - Art Commission of the City of New York, 1913; 21655 (Box 621)
    - Boston Architectural Club Exposition, 1902; 21654 (Box 621)
    - Chicago Architectural Club, 1900-1920; 21653 (Box 621)
    - Chicago Architectural Exhibition, 1919-1927; 21652 (Box 621)
    - Commission of Fine Arts, 1910-1934; 21651 (Box 621-626)
    - Committee of One Hundred, 1914-1918; 21650 (Box 626)
    - Council of Fine Arts, 1909; 21649 (Box 626)
    - Detroit Architectural Club, 1900; 21648 (Box 626)
    - Fine Arts Federation of New York, 1902-1918; 21647 (Box 626)
    - Great Georgian Houses of America, 1932-1933; 21646 (Box 626)
    - International Congress of Architects, 1905-1930; 21645 (Box 626-627)
    - Museum of Architecture, 1906; 21644 (Box 627)
    - National Academy Association, 1912-1931; 21643 (Box 627)
    - National Academy of Art, 1909; 21642 (Box 627)
    - National Academy of Design, 1909-1933; 21641 (Box 627-631)
    - National Arts Club, 1913-1922; 21640 (Box 632)
    - National Arts Service League, Undated; 21639 (Box 632)
    - National Conservation Association, 1910; 21638 (Box 632)
    - National Conservation Commission, 1908-1913; 21637 (Box 632)
    - National Conservation Congress, 1910-1912; 21636 (Box 632)
    - National Institute of Arts & Letters, 1907-1934; 21635 (Box 632)
    - National Sculpture Society, 1915-1933; 21634 (Box 632)
    - New Jersey State Board of Architects, 1902-1905; 21633 (Box 632)
    - New York Building Congress, 1928-1929; 21632 (Box 632)
    - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, 1914-1915; 21631 (Box 632)
    - Pittsburg Architectural Club, 1900; 21630 (Box 632)
    - T-Square Club, 1899-1925; 21629 (Box 632)
    - Toronto Architectural Eighteen Club, 1901; 21628 (Box 632)
    - Washington Architectural Club, 1901, 1906; 21627 (Box 632)
  - Subseries II. Bound Volumes, 21622
    This subseries contains four letterbooks of outgoing correspondence regarding the American Institute of Architects, the Commission of Fine Arts, and the National Academy of Design. Many of these volumes are fragile and access is dependent upon the judgment of the print room staff.
    - American Institute of Architects-Letterbook, 1907-1909; 21625 (Volume 388)
    - Commission of Fine Arts- Letterbook, 1912-1918; 21624 (Volume 389)
    - National Academy of Design- Letterbook, 1926-1934; 21623 (Volume 390-391)
- Series IV. Personal Files, 21541
  This series includes Gilbert's files that do not reflect his architectural work or professional life. The material includes letters among his friends and family as well as important papers from his personal life.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 21581
    This subseries consists of incoming letters to Cass Gilbert. The correspondence includes personal letters from family, friends, and colleagues relating to matters such as his insurance, the purchase and upkeep of his properties, automobile maintenance, and family finances. Many of the letters also document his donations to organizations such as anti-prohibition groups and patriotic organizations in World War I. Letters from his family include letters from his wife Julia Finch Gilbert, letters from his brother Samuel relating to Gilbert's insurance policies, and letters from his brother Charles related to property. Letters from other family members are included. Correspondence from colleagues includes letters from Edwin Blashfield, Alexander Calder, Daniel Chester French, F.H. Olmstead, Sir Aston Webb, etc. Some letters to Cass Gilbert from 1918-1919 relate to Cass Gilbert Jr.'s service in WWI. Incoming correspondence to other family members is also included. These include many sympathy letters to the Gilbert family after the death of Cass in 1934.
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), Undated, 1887-1902; 21620 (Box 633)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1903-1907; 21619 (Box 634)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1905-1907; 21618 (Box 635)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1907-1908; 21617 (Box 636)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1909-1910; 21616 (Box 637)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1911-1912; 21615 (Box 638)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1913-1914; 21614 (Box 639)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1914-1915; 21613 (Box 640)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1915-1916; 21612 (Box 641)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1916-1917; 21611 (Box 642)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1917; 21610 (Box 643)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1917-1918; 21609 (Box 644)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1918; 21608 (Box 645)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1918-1919; 21607 (Box 646)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1919-1920; 21606 (Box 647)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1920-1921; 21605 (Box 648)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1922; 21604 (Box 649)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1923; 21603 (Box 650)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1924; 21602 (Box 651)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1924-1925; 21601 (Box 652)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1925-1926; 21600 (Box 653)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1926-1927; 21599 (Box 654)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1927-1928; 21598 (Box 655)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1928-1929; 21597 (Box 656)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1929-1930; 21596 (Box 657)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1930-1931; 21595 (Box 658)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1931; 21594 (Box 659)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1932-1933; 21593 (Box 660)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert), 1933-1934; 21592 (Box 661)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert, Jr.), Undated, 1918-1934; 21591 (Box 662)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert, Jr.), 1934; 21590 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Julia Finch Gilbert), 1919-1935; 21589 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Emily Gilbert), 1928; 21588 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Julia Gilbert Post), 1931, 1934; 21587 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Read, R), 1912-1933; 21586 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Margaret Gilbert Higgins), 1929-1931; 21585 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Mrs. Cass Gilbert, Jr), 1918-1919; 21584 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Samuel Gilbert), 1918, 1934; 21583 (Box 663)
    - Correspondence (to Cass Gilbert III), 1928; 21582 (Box 663)
  - Subseries II: Clubs and Associations, 21575
    This subseries contains organizational materials documenting Gilbert's work with groups including the Carnegie Institute,the Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation, and the Parks and Playgrounds Association. The subseries includes correspondence, minutes, and reports for the organizations.
    - Carnegie Institute, Minutes and Reports, 1925; 21580 (Box 663-665)
    - Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation, Minutes, 1919-1931; 21579 (Box 665)
    - Parks and Playgrounds Associations, Minutes, 1908-1909; 21578 (Box 666)
    - Century Association, Reports of the Building Committee, 1924; 21577 (Box 666)
    - Various Organizations, 1915-1932; 21576 (Box 666)
  - Subseries III: Financial Documents, 21571
    The financial documents include bills and receipts as well as tax and estate papers of the Gilbert family.
    - Bills and Receipts, 1900-1918; 21574 (Box 666)
    - Estate Papers, 1934-1937; 21573 (Box 667)
    - Tax Assessments, 1912-1933; 21572 (Box 667)
  - Subseries IV: Invitations, 21568
    This subseries contains invitations to events from friends and organizations. Included are invitations to the White House by Presidents Theodore Roosevelt and Herbert Hoover. A small amount of invitations by Cass Gilbert are also included.
    - Invitations to Cass Gilbert (including White House Invitations), Undated, 1902-1934; 21570 (Box 667-670)
    - Invitations by Cass Gilbert and Responses Received, 1925-1930; 21569 (Box 670)
  - Subseries V: Speeches and Writings, 21563
    This subseries consists of speeches given by Cass Gilbert, usually his acceptance speeches of awards and honors. It also includes poems and prefaces to books by Cass Gilbert and other unidentified writers.
    - Speeches, 1912-1933; 21567 (Box 670-671)
    - Speeches by Other Authors, 1923-1939; 21566 (Box 671)
    - Prefaces to Books, 1927; 21565 (Box 671)
    - Poems by Cass Gilbert and Others, 1905-1930; 21564 (Box 671)
  - Subseries VI: Property Information, 21557
    The property information includes agreements, specifications, contractor information, and drawings for property owned by Cass Gilbert and the Gilbert family.
    - #1-#5 East 94th Street, 1925-1931; 21562 (Box 671)
    - 71 Floral Street, 1900-1916; 21561 (Box 671)
    - Huntington, Long Island, 1905; 21560 (Box 671)
    - James House, 1931-1932; 21559 (Box 671)
    - Shepaug Farm, 1927-1928; 21558 (Box 671)
  - Subseries VII: Brochures, 21555
    This subseries includes brochures saved by Cass Gilbert regarding water pumps, anti-prohibition organizations, and other groups.
    - Brochures- Water Pumps, Anti-Prohibition Organizations, Proposed Public Works Department, etc., Undated, 1920-1931; 21556 (Box 671-672)
  - Subseries VIII: Clippings, 21553
    The clippings include articles regarding politics and architecture. A folder of obituaries for Cass Gilbert is also included.